Inventory of the John Amar Shishmanian papers
Hoover Institution Archives
John Amar Shishmanian papers
1879-1946
41003
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box, 4 envelopes (1.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to the Armenian-Turkish conflict at the end of World War I, and to the Armenian question at the Paris Peace Conference.
Shishmanian, John Amar, 1882-1945.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1941.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
John Shishmanian was born in 1882 in Lexington, Kentucky, to George N. and Lucy McClelland Shishmanian. Shishmanian grew up in Constantinople, where his father worked as a missionary. He graduated from Robert College and returned to the United States to attend university. Shishmanian graduated from the University of Kentucky in 1903, then studied law at the University of Virginia from 1903 to 1906 and registered at Stanford University in the fall of 1910.
Preceding the entrance of the United States into World War I, Shishmanian went to France as a member of the American ambulance field service. He then enlisted in the French Army and rose to the rank of second lieutenant, the highest rank possible for a non-citizen. Following action at the Battle of Verdun, Shishmanian and other French officers were sent to Cyprus to prepare Armenian volunteers for the French Armenian Legion, later known as the Légion Arménienne.
The Légion Arménienne served along the Eastern front in Palestine, Syria, and Cilicia in southeastern Anatolia. For his actions in the Palestine campaign, Shishmanian was awarded the Croix de Guerre medal. In June of 1920, with his term of service completed and the disbandment of the Légion Arménienne, Shishmanian was asked by the French to remain in Adana, Turkey, for three months, from June 10 to September 10, 1920. Shishmanian's task was to organize local Armenian volunteers to defend Adana from attacks by Kemalist rebels.
Despite his success in Adana, Shishmanian was placed under arrest by the French on September 22, 1920, and expelled from Cilicia. It is unclear whether this was due to Shishmanian's refusal to follow an order or the changing policies of the French in the region. Shishmanian's freedom was eventually secured through the interventions of his parents and Jouett Shouse, then undersecretary of the U.S. Treasury. Shishmanian returned to the United States and lived the remainder of his life in Fresno, California.
In recognition of these Armenian volunteers, the French government gave certain assurances to the Délégation Nationale Arménienne based on an Allied victory. In particular, the Cilicia region would become an autonomous Armenian republic under French protection. At the conclusion of the war, the peace treaty terms defined at the Paris Peace Conference did not create an autonomous Armenian republic, and control of the region was ceded to the new Republic of Turkey.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers are comprised of correspondence, documents, printed matter, and photographs related to Shishmanian's service in the French Army during World War I, the Armenian-Turkish conflict, and the Armenian question at the Paris Peace Conference.
The correspondence focuses on Shishmanian's service in the French army, including a handwritten letter from Viscount Allenby, the commander-in-chief of the Egyptian Expeditionary Force, and a letter of thanks from Boghus Nubar, chairman of the Armenian National Assembly. In addition there is the correspondence of Georgia Cutler, sister of Leland W. Cutler a trustee of Stanford University and President of the Board.
Translations of the original documents are sometimes available.
The majority of the 130 photographs document Shishmanian's time as an officer in the Légion Arménienne during World War I. There are also photographs of his time in France prior to enlisting in the French army, notable Armenians, and photos obtained from the Kaloustian family depicting Armenians living along the Euphrates river. Additionally there is a photograph of Lucy McClelland Shishmanian in 1879 and one of John Shishmanian in 1944.
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Armenian massacres, 1915-1923.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; Armenia (Republic)--History.
- Correspondence, 1917-1946, undated
  - General correspondence, 1917-1934 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    Scope and Contents note
    In English, French, Armenian and Turkish.
  - Georgia Cutler correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box-folder 1: 3-4)
    Includes authorized statements from Shishmanian to Cutler.
- Documents, 1919-1920, circa 1918, undated
  - Military related papers, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    In English, French, and Armenian.
  - Délégation Nationale Arménienne, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    In English and French.
  - Memorandum to the Ottoman delegation, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Notes, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Maps, circa 1918 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    In English, French, and Armenian. Drawn by Shishmanian.
  - Armenian folksong, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - The Last Dance, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Written by Minas Tcheraz and translated into English by Shishmanian for the Armenian Mirror-Spectator newspaper.
- Printed material, 1919-1943, undated
  In English and Armenian.
  - Treaties, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "The Armenian Question Before the Peace Conference,", 1919 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Magazines, 1921-1943 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Bulletins and pamphlets, 1942-1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Clippings, 1919-1943, undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
    Arranged alphabetically and thereunder chronologically.
- Newspapers, 1919-1934 (Box 2)
  In English and Armenian. Arranged chronologically.
- USSR in Construction, magazine, 1932 (Box 2)
- Flag, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1879-1944 (bulk, 1903-1920)
  - Pre-World War I photographs along with ones taken in France, Cyprus and Palestine, 1879-1944 (Envelope A)
  - Photographs taken in Palestine and Syria, 1918-1921 (Envelope B(1))
  - Photographs taken in Adana, Syria and Egypt, 1919-1920 (Envelope B(2))
  - Photographs of notable Armenians, along with photographs of Musa Dagh commemoration at Suez, Egypt, 1920, undated (Envelope m*C)